<!--
  $RCSfile: CH_tasks.xml,v $
  $Revision: 1.6 $
  $Author: langer $
  $Date: 2011-05-02 15:47:04 $

  This software was produced by NIST, an agency of the
  U.S. government, and by statute is not subject to copyright in the
  United States.  Recipients of this software assume all
  responsibilities associated with its operation, modification and
  maintenance. However, to facilitate maintenance we ask that before
  distributing modified versions of this software, you first contact
  the authors at oof_manager@nist.gov.
-->


<chapter id="Chapter-Tasks">
  <title>Task Pages</title>

  <section id="Section-Tasks-Overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      This chapter describes how to operate the &oof2; main GUI
      window.  All operations in the GUI have an associated <link
      linkend="Section-ScriptGUI">command</link> which is discussed in
      <xref linkend="Chapter-Reference"/>.  That chapter is the place
      to go for detailed discussions about what the commands do and
      how their arguments are defined.  In this chapter the section
      describing each GUI page provides an overview of the page and
      discusses any GUI-specific issues, but does not provide details
      of how the command works or how its arguments are defined.  Each
      section does, however, link to the relevant pieces of <xref
      linkend="Chapter-Reference"/> where the details may be found.
    </para>
    <para>
      The main &oof2; window consists of a menu bar, a navigation bar,
      and a <emphasis>Task Page</emphasis> (<xref
      linkend="Figure-MainWindow"/>). The navigation bar switches
      between different Task Pages.  Each Task Page addresses a
      fundamental step in an &oof2; calculation.  The pages are
      arranged, more or less, in the order in which you'll use them.
    </para>

    <figure id="Figure-MainWindow">
      <title>The Main &oof2; Window</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="FIGURES/gui/mainwindow.png" format="PNG"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
	  <phrase>Annotated image of the main oof2 window.</phrase>
	</textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <note>
      <para>
	Your version of &oof2; may not look exactly like the
	illustrations in this manual. You can change the color scheme,
	widget set, and font used in the GUI via the <xref
	linkend="MenuItem-OOF.Settings.Fonts"/> menu and <xref
	linkend="MenuItem-OOF.Settings.Theme"/> command.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      The Menu Bar at the top of the window in <xref
      linkend="Figure-MainWindow"/> (highlighted in light green)
      includes general purpose commands.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Task Page at the bottom (highlighted in yellow in the
      figure) contains buttons and widgets for working on a particular
      aspect of &oof2;.  Each page is described in its own section of
      this manual.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Navigation Bar between the menu bar and the task page
      (highlighted in light blue) contains a central pull down menu
      for choosing Task Pages.  The buttons immediately to the left
      and right of the Task menu can be used to quickly switch to the
      next and previous pages in the order in which they're listed in
      the central menu.  The outer pair of buttons also switch to the
      next and previous pages, but in the order in which the pages
      were visited.
    </para>
    <para>
      Many of the Task Pages are divided into separate panes.  The
      divider between the panes may be dragged to change their sizes.
    </para>
  </section>

  &TPmicro;
  &TPimage;
  &TPpixsel;
  &TPactive;
  &TPmaterial;
  <!-- &TPinterfaces; -->
  &TPskel;
  &TPpinnodes;
  &TPskelsel;
  &TPskelbdy;
  &TPfemesh;
  &TPfields;
  &TPbdycond;
  &TPscheduled;
  &TPsolver;
  &TPanalysis;
  &TPbdyanalysis;

</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  sgml-omittag:t
  sgml-shorttag:t 
  sgml-namecase-general:nil
  sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
  sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
  sgml-indent-step:2
  sgml-indent-data:t
  sgml-parent-document:("man_oof2.xml" "book" "chapter")
  sgml-exposed-tags:nil
  sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
  End:
-->
