<!--
  This software was produced by NIST, an agency of the
  U.S. government, and by statute is not subject to copyright in the
  United States.  Recipients of this software assume all
  responsibilities associated with its operation, modification and
  maintenance. However, to facilitate maintenance we ask that before
  distributing modified versions of this software, you first contact
  the authors at oof_manager@ctcms.nist.gov.
-->

<section id="Section-Graphics-PixelSelection" role="toolbox">
  <title>The Pixel Selection Toolbox</title>
  <para>
    The Pixel Selection Toolbox selects pixels in the topmost &micro;
    or &image; displayed in the Canvas.  It augments the <link
    linkend="Section-Tasks-Pixel_Selection">Pixel Selection Task
    Page</link> by providing ways of selecting pixels with the mouse.
  </para>
  <figure id="Figure-pixelseltoolbox">
    <title>The Pixel Selection Toolbox</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="FIGURES/gfx/pixelselection.png"
	               format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	    <para>
	      The Pixel Selection Toolbox, on the left, and a selection in
	      progress in the Canvas, on the right.
	    </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    As shown in <xref linkend="Figure-pixelseltoolbox"/>, the Pixel
    Selection Toolbox consists of two regions.  The upper region
    contains a pull-down menu labelled <guilabel>Method</guilabel> for
    choosing a pixel selection technique.  These techniques correspond
    to commands in the <xref
    linkend="MenuItem-OOF.Graphics_n.Toolbox.Pixel_Select"/> menu.
    The region immediately below the <guilabel>Method</guilabel> menu
    is for setting the parameters of the chosen selection method.
    After choosing a method, clicking or clicking and dragging the
    mouse on the Canvas will invoke the corresponding command to
    select pixels.
  </para>
  <para>
    The shift and control keys on the keyboard can be held down while
    making a selection.  They modify the selection operation as shown
    in <xref linkend="Table:ShiftCtrl"/>.  The shift key retains the
    previous selection, the control key toggles the previous
    selection, and both keys together take the intersection of the
    previous and the new selections.
  </para>
  <para>
    The four buttons labelled <link
    linkend="MenuItem-OOF.Graphics_n.Toolbox.Pixel_Select.Undo"><guibutton>Undo</guibutton></link>,
    <link
    linkend="MenuItem-OOF.Graphics_n.Toolbox.Pixel_Select.Redo"><command>Redo</command></link>,
    <link
    linkend="MenuItem-OOF.Graphics_n.Toolbox.Pixel_Select.Clear"><guibutton>Clear</guibutton></link>
    and <link
    linkend="MenuItem-OOF.Graphics_n.Toolbox.Pixel_Select.Invert"><guibutton>Invert</guibutton></link>
    also correspond to commands in the <xref
    linkend="MenuItem-OOF.Graphics_n.Toolbox.Pixel_Select"/> menu.
    These functions are all available on the <link
    linkend="Section-Tasks-Pixel_Selection">Pixel Selection Task
    Page</link>, but are duplicated in the Toolbox for convenience.
  </para>
  <para id="Section-Graphics-PixelSelection-History">
    The box labelled <guilabel>History</guilabel> shows the
    position(s) of the last mouse click in <link
    linkend="Section-Concepts-Microstructure-Coordinates">physical</link>
    coordinates.  It displays both the point where the mouse was
    depressed (<guilabel>down</guilabel>) and where it was released
    (<guilabel>up</guilabel>).  If the selection method did not use
    one of the coordinates, the Toolbox displays
    <userinput>--</userinput>.
  </para>
  <para>
    The <guibutton>Prev</guibutton> and <guibutton>Next</guibutton>
    buttons cycle through both the mouse click history and the history
    of selection methods.
  </para>
  <para>
    The <guibutton>Repeat</guibutton> button simulates a mouse click
    at the coordinates shown in the <guilabel>down</guilabel> and
    <guilabel>up</guilabel> boxes, using the technique and parameters
    currently selected in the <guilabel>Method</guilabel> menu.  It's
    possible to change any or all of the parameters, including the
    mouse coordinates, before hitting <guibutton>Repeat</guibutton>.
    To change the mouse coordinates, just type new values into the
    <guilabel>down</guilabel> and <guilabel>up</guilabel> boxes.  If
    the current selection technique requires a coordinate for which
    there is no data in the box, the <guibutton>Repeat</guibutton>
    button will be unavailable.
  </para>
  <para>
    The shift and control keys can be held down while the
    <guibutton>Repeat</guibutton> button is pressed.  They have the
    same effect that they do while clicking on the Canvas.
  </para>
  <para>
    The way in which the selected pixels are highlighted in the Canvas
    may be changed by using the &layereditor; to alter the <xref
    linkend="RegisteredClass-BitmapOverlayDisplayMethod"/> display method that's
    assigned to the Pixel Selection category.  It will be necessary to
    enable <link
    linkend="MenuItem-OOF.Graphics_n.Settings.List_All_Layers"><command>List
    All Layers</command></link> in the <link
    linkend="Section-Graphics-MenuBar">Settings menu</link> first.
  </para>
</section>


<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  sgml-omittag:t
  sgml-shorttag:t 
  sgml-namecase-general:nil
  sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
  sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
  sgml-indent-step:2
  sgml-indent-data:t
  sgml-parent-document:("man_oof2.xml" "book" "chapter" "section")
  sgml-exposed-tags:nil
  sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
  End:
-->
